Guide to the Harriet Silverman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harriet Silverman papers
1917-1941
MS 1763
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, publications, and research material which document Harriet Silverman's activities as director and educational secretary of the Workers' Health Bureau of America and executive-secretary of the People's National Health Committee.
Silverman, Harriet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were transferred from the George Rosen papers in 1999.
Biographical / Historical
Harriet Silverman was an activist in New York City involved in labor and left-wing social and political movements in the 1920s and 1930s. As director and educational secretary of the Workers' Health Bureau of New York and executive-secretary of the People's National Health Committee, Silverman wrote articles, reports, and pamphlets regarding the rights of workers. She was a delegate of several conventions and conferences including the New York state convention of the American Labor Party, the American Investigation Committee on Russian Women, the National Health Conference, and the White House Conference on Children in Democracy. Harriet Silverman died in New York City in May 1940.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged alphabetically by organization.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, publications, and research material which document Harriet Silverman's activities as director and educational secretary of the Workers' Health Bureau of America and executive-secretary of the People's National Health Committee.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Labor unions and public health; Public health advisory groups; Silverman, Harriet; People's National Health Committee (United States); Worker's Health Bureau of America
- Inventory, 1917-1941; Accession 2000-M-132
  Scope and Contents
  The papers consist of materials created and accumulated by Silverman while serving as director of the Workers' Health Bureau of America and executive-secretary of the People's National Health Committee (PNHC). The files relating to the PNHC comprise the bulk of the collection. The files are comprised of correspondence, reports, and publications. A significant portion of the files consists of materials relating to the Wagner Health Bill, for which the PNHC was created to support. Files related to the bill include correspondence, drafts of the bill, recommendations for amendments, and research material. Another significant portion of the files relates to the People's Health Bulletin. The Bulletin files consist primarily of materials for inclusion submitted by various people involved in workers' health rights.
  Files documenting Silverman's activities as director and education secretary of the Workers' Health Bureau of America include correspondence, publications, and reports. The correspondence consists primarily of correspondence between Silverman and Grace Burnham and Charlotte Todes, executive secretary and organizing secretary of the Workers' Health Bureau respectively. One file of correspondence regarding a study of women in industry is listed at the end of the correspondence. The administrative reports comprise another pertinent portion of the files. The reports document the activities, goals and dissolution of the Workers' Health Bureau of America.
  - American Association for Labor Legislation, 1936-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Medical Association, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Public Welfare Association, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - People's National Health Committee
    - General
      - Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      - Fundraising, 1939-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Publications, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Reports, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Conferences
      - Philadelphia's Health Needs, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - White House Conference on Children in Democracy, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    - People's Health Bulletin, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13-20)
    - Legislation, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Photographs [Farm Security Administration], 1939 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Publications, 1925-1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - Wagner Health Bill
      - General, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Amendments and objections, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Background material, 1938, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Campaign on, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Clippings, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Conference, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Notes [miscellaneous], 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Speeches, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - United Auto Workers Medical Research Institute, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Workers' Health Bureau of America
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1924, 1928, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Burnham, Grace, 1924-1926 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Todes, Charlotte, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Publications, 1924-1927 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Reports, 1925-1928, undated (Box 3, Folder 40-43)
    - Women in industry study, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Women's rights, 1917-1930 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Worker's rights, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 46)